<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning Techniques</title>
    <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Learning Techniques</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mind</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/brain/mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/brain/mind/</guid>
      <description>Your mind and thinking is either in focused mode or in diffuse mode. It can&amp;rsquo;t be in the two at the same time. Alternating between them is an important thing during learning. Forcing yourself to stay in the focused mode for too long won&amp;rsquo;t give you better results than when you regularly switch to the diffuse mode.
Focused Mode In the focused mode, your mind is fully focused on one task.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/resources/time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/resources/time/</guid>
      <description> Time is a precious resource. To make the best use of your time, schedule the time you want to focus, e.g. by using the pomodoro technique as well as the breaks. Also don&amp;rsquo;t forget to schedule the finishing time for the day. Setting this small deadline will help you to focus and get things done.
Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memory</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/brain/memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/brain/memory/</guid>
      <description>Working Memory The working memory (or short term memory) holds what you are currently processing. The items stored in this memory are there only temporarily and can be pushed away when you want to store other information. Those memories vanish quickly and you have to repeat them to keep them in your working memory. Scientists assume that you have four slots where you can store items. Those items can also be chunks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Willpower</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/resources/willpower/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/resources/willpower/</guid>
      <description> Willpower is an important resource. You need willpower to (no complete list):
 change habits do something you don&amp;rsquo;t like make decisions  It will be consumed during the day! Handle with care.
Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Habits</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/brain/habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/brain/habits/</guid>
      <description>Habits have the following structure:
1. Cue This triggers the whole habit. For example if you leave your house you will most likely lock the door. Probably you won&amp;rsquo;t even think about that.
2. Routine After being triggered, you go into zombie mode and the routine will kick off. In our example you will lock the door.
3. Reward You will be rewarded with a good feeling. In our case you will be rewarded with a warm feeling that your house is secure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/resources/motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/resources/motivation/</guid>
      <description>First of all: You can learn a lot of things, even things that you think are out of your field of competence. Having a high motivation for what you want to learn makes things much more easy for you. When you are not into what you want to learn, you might have a hard time. But be aware, not everybody is fond of a task all the time, even it is part of the big picture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/resources/sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/resources/sleep/</guid>
      <description> This is not a resource. But it resets your resources!
During sleep, your brain erases the less important parts of what you stored during the day and helps you to strengthen the things that are important to you. It builds the neural structures, namely synapses, that are required to enhance the skills you are currently learning.
Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operate on Habits</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/operate_on_habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/operate_on_habits/</guid>
      <description> Research shows that habits can be changed, deleted or new ones can be implemented. It uses willpower, but if done right, you need it only at one specific timepoint. This can be used to remove procrastination!
How-To Remove Habit  Find the cue Remove what triggers the cue Belief in yourself that you have the power to remove it ;-) Repeat until removed  Change Habit  Find the cue Focus on different routine Reward yourself Belief in yourself that you have the power to change it ;-) Repeat until changed  Implement Habit  Find a cue Practice wished routine Reward yourself Belief in yourself that you have the power to implement it ;-) Repeat until implemented  What For  Change your habits Get rid of procrastination  Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interleaving</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/interleaving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/interleaving/</guid>
      <description> Interleaving is a meta learning method where you vary between different learning techniques. Using different methods can help you deepen the task you are working on.
How-To  Try different learning techniques during learning one item, e.g.  visual learning, e.g. by watch a lecture writing things down by listening, e.g. somebody explaining things explaining things to others &amp;hellip;   What For  Bringing things to long term memory  Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chunking</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/chunking/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/chunking/</guid>
      <description>Chunks are compact packages of information that are easy accessible for the mind. They are part of the bigger picture that you want to form, but easier to grasp for the focused mind. Chunking is the technique to form chunks and to connect them.
How-To  Break your big picture down into managable tasks. It is important to understand the big picture! Alternate between the following two:  Practice these tasks in focused mode using pomodoro technique and spaced repetition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deliberate Practice</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/deliberate_practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/deliberate_practice/</guid>
      <description>In deliberate practice one focuses on the task that is practiced and seeks always to improve the skill he is working on. This means that once one gets comfortable with a level that he pushes himself to go for the next level. This is different to normal practice which could include mindless repetitions and repeating what you already learned. Deliberate practice is more exhausting but leads quicker to better learning results.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dreaming</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/dreaming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/dreaming/</guid>
      <description> When you dream about something you can strengthen in your brain the item you are dreaming about (see also sleep). Thus, we need to prime your dreaming experience.
How-To  Learn the thing you want to be strengthend right before you go to sleep.  What For  Transfer to long term memory  Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memory Palace</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/memorization/memory_palace/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/memorization/memory_palace/</guid>
      <description>The memory palace technique helps you building groups of unrelated things to be stored together. Once grouped together, they just occupy one slot of your working memory. The underlying assumption is, that the mind can remember images better than anything else because from an evolutionary point of view we are build for remembering paths for orientation.
How-To  Imagine a large house that you know by heart Place the items you want to remember in the rooms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pomodoro</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/focusing/pomodoro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/focusing/pomodoro/</guid>
      <description> The Pomodoro technique, named after a kitchen timer, is a technique that helps you focus and battle procrastination.
How-To  Set your timer to 25 minutes. Turn off all possible sources of interruption, if possible. Work focused for the time on ONE task. Take a break for a couple of minutes and reward yourself, e.g. with web-browsing Repeat  What For  Trains focused mode Helps against procrastination  Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Process-orienting</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/focusing/process-orienting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/focusing/process-orienting/</guid>
      <description> Accomplishing a task can be done in two ways:
 process-oriented or product-oriented  When you focus on the outcome (product), this seems to put more stress on you as when you focus on the process of accomplishing the product. It is more likely that you will get into a flow and dodge procrastination.
As Jesus/Konfuzius said: The journey is the reward.
How-To  Look at the actual work that needs to be done to accomplish the product Use the pomodoro technique to focus on the work  What For  Getting into the flow Avoid procrastination  Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recall</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/recall/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/recall/</guid>
      <description> Recalling is a method where you test yourself about the things you just learned. It should prevent you from the illusion of competence, a pitfall where you think you are an expert in a field by having read books about that field but you didn&amp;rsquo;t do any problem solving yourself.
How-To  Learn or read an item or paragraph Try to test yourself about what you just learned  What For  Avoid illusion of competence  Links </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spaced Repetition</title>
      <link>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/spaced_repetition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stolpeo.github.com/learning-techniques/tools/new_skill/spaced_repetition/</guid>
      <description>Spaced repetition helps you to store things in your long term memory. It is more efficient to repeat things for a shorter time every or every few days rather than practice one time for a longer time period. A pomodoro each day is better than binge learning!
How-To  Define your practice routine for the item you want to store permanently Make a timetable over one or more weeks where you schedule, say, a pomodoro a day for the first days and then a pomodoro every few days with incrementing spaces.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>